欢迎回来。
So welcome back.
今天我们将涵盖调试和分析。
Today we are gonna cover debugging and profiling.
在我开始之前，我们将再次提醒您填写调查问卷。
Before I get into it we're gonna make another reminder to fill in the survey.
我们想从您那里得到的主要问题之一是：
Just one of the main things we want to get from you is questions,
在最后一天，我们会回答来自您们的问题，
because the last day is gonna be questions from you guys:
包括我们没有涉及到的问题或者您希望我们深入讨论的问题。
about things that we haven't covered, or like you want us to kind of talk more in depth.
我们获得的问题越多，我们就可以让这一部分更加有趣，
The more questions we get, the more interesting we can make that section,
请您填写调查问卷。
so please go on and fill in the survey.
今天的讲座将涵盖很多主题。
So today's lecture is gonna be a lot of topics.
所有主题都围绕着一个概念展开：
All the topics revolve around the concept of
当您的程序存在错误时，您应该怎么做。
what do you do when you have a program that has some bugs.
在编程时，
Which is most of the time, like when you are programming,
您大部分时间都在考虑如何实现某些功能，
you're kind of thinking about how you implement something
但是修复程序中的所有问题需要花费很长时间。
and there's like a half life of fixing all the issues that that program has.
即使您的程序按照您的预期运行，
And even if your program behaves like you want,
它可能也会非常缓慢，或者占用很多资源。
it might be that it's really slow, or it's taking a lot of resources in the process.
今天我们将看到许多不同的解决这些问题的方法。
So today we're gonna see a lot of different approaches of dealing with these problems.
首先，第一部分是关于调试的。
So first, the first section is on debugging.
调试可以有许多不同的方法，有各种各样的方式...
Debugging can be done in many different ways, there are all kinds of...
几乎所有计算机科学学生都将使用的最简单的方法就是：
The most simple approach that, pretty much, all CS students will go through, will be just:
您有一些代码，它的行为不符合您的预期，
you have some code, and it's not behaving like you want,
所以您通过添加打印语句来探索代码。
so you probe the code by addingmprint statements.
这被称为“printf调试”，它运行得非常好。
This is called "printf debugging" and it works pretty well.
老实说，我经常使用它，
Like, I have to be honest, I use it a lot of the time
因为设置简单，反馈快。
because of how simple to set up and how quick the feedback can be.
printf调试的一个问题是您可能会获得大量输出，
One of the issues with printf debugging is that you can get a lot of output
而您可能并不希望获得这么多输出。
and maybe you don't want to get as much output as you're getting.
人们已经考虑了稍微复杂一些的printf调试方法之一，
There has... people have thought of slightly more complex ways of doing printf debugging
即通常称为“日志记录”。
and one of these ways is what is usually referred to as "logging".
与printf调试相比，使用日志记录的优点在于，当您创建日志记录时，
So the advantage of doing logging versus doing printf debugging is that,  when you're creating logs,
您并不一定是因为要修复特定的问题，
you're not necessarily creating the logs because there's a specific issue you want to fix;
而是因为您构建了一个更复杂的软件系统，
it's mostly because you have built a more complex software system
并且想在某些事件发生时记录下来。
and you want to log when some events happen.
使用日志记录库的一个核心优点是您可以定义严重性级别，
One of the core advantages of using a logging library is
并且可以根据这些级别进行过滤。
that you can can define severity levels, and you can filter based on those.
让我们看一个如何实现这样一个示例。
Let's see an example of how we can do something like that.
是的，一切都符合预期。
Yeah, everything fits here.
这是一个非常愚蠢的例子：
This is a really silly example:
我们将随机抽取一些数字，并根据数字的值记录数字的值，
We're just gonna sample random numbers and,  depending on the value of the number,
（可以解释为“错误程度”）
that we can interpret as a kind of "how wrong things are going".
然后我们可以看看发生了什么。
We're going to log the value of the number and then we can see what is going on.
我需要禁用这些格式化程序...
I need to disable these formatters...
如果我们按原样执行代码，
And if we were just to execute the code as it is,
我们只会得到输出并且不断获得更多的输出。
we just get the output and we just keep getting more and more output.
但是你必须盯着它看，并理解正在发生的事情。
But you have to kind of stare at it and make sense of what is going on,
我们不知道printf之间的相对时间，
and we don't know what is the relative timing between printfs,
也不知道这是仅仅是一条信息消息
we don't really know whether this is just an information message
还是有错误发生的消息。
or a message of whether something went wrong.
如果我们进去，然后撤销，不是那个...
If we just go in, and undo, not that one...
就是那个，我们可以设置格式化程序。
That one, we can set that formatter.
现在输出看起来更像是这样：
Now the output looks something more like this
例如，如果你正在使用多个不同的模块进行编程，
So for example, if you have several different modules that you are programming with,
你可以使用不同的级别来标识它们。
you can identify them with like different levels.
这里，我们有调试级别、关键信息、不同级别。
Here, we have, we have debug levels, we have critical info, different levels.
这可能很方便，因为我们可能只关心错误消息。
And it might be handy because here we might only care about the error messages.
就像那些...
Like those are like, the...
我们一直在编写代码，到目前为止一切顺利，突然出现了一些错误。
We have been working on our code, so far so good, and suddenly we get some error.
我们可以记录下来以确定它发生在哪里。
We can log that to identify where it's happening.
但是也许有很多信息消息，
But maybe there's a lot of information messages,
但我们可以通过将级别更改为错误级别来处理它们。
but we can deal with that by just changing the level to error level.
现在，如果我们再次运行它，我们只会在输出中得到那些错误，
And now if we were to run this again, we are only going to get those errors in the output,
我们只需浏览它们以理解正在发生的事情。
and we can just look through those to make sense of what is going on.
当你处理日志时，另一个非常有用的工具是......
Another really useful tool when you're dealing with logs is...
随着你的观察，它变得更容易了，
As you kind of look at this, it has become easier
因为现在我们有了可以快速识别的关键和错误级别。
because now we have this critical and error levels that we can quickly identify.
但由于人类是相当视觉化的生物，
But since humans are fairly visual creatures,
你可以使用终端中的颜色来识别这些内容。
one thing that you can do is use colors from your terminal to identify these things.
所以现在，改变格式化程序，我稍微改变了输出的格式。
So now, changing the formatter, what I've done is slightly change how the output is formatted.
当我这样做时，现在每当我收到一个警告消息时，它是用黄色编码的；
When I do that, now whenever I get a warning message, it's color coded by yellow;
每当我收到像错误一样的消息时，它是模糊的红色；
whenever I get like an error, faded red;
当它是关键的时候，我有一个加粗的红色，表示有错误发生了。
and when it's critical, I have a bold red indicating something went wrong.
在这里，输出非常短，
And here it's a really short output,
但是当你开始有成千上万行的日志时，
but when you start having thousands and thousands of lines of log,
这并不是不切实际的，而且在许多应用程序中每天都会发生，
which is not unrealistic and happens every single day in a lot of apps,
快速浏览并确定错误或红色区域的位置可以非常有用。
quickly browsing through them and identifying where the error or the red patches are can be really useful.
一个快速的旁注是，你可能会好奇终端是如何显示这些颜色的。
A quick aside is, you might be curious about how the terminal is displaying these colors.
归根结底，终端只输出字符。
At the end of the day, the terminal is only outputting characters.
这个程序，还有像LS这样的其他程序，它们都有很多花哨的颜色，
Like, how is this program or how are other programs, like LS,  that has all these fancy colors.
那么它们是如何告诉终端使用这些不同的颜色的呢？
How are they telling the terminal that it should use these different colors?
其实这些工具所做的事情并不是非常复杂，大致上是这样的。
This is nothing extremely fancy, what these tools are doing, is something along these lines.
这里有……我可以清除其余的输出，这样我们就可以专注于这个问题。
Here we have... I can clear the rest of the output, so we can focus on this.
这里有一些特殊字符，一些转义字符，
There's some special characters, some escape characters here,
然后是一些文本，最后是一些其他特殊字符。
then we have some text and then we have some other special characters.
如果我们执行这行代码，我们就会得到一个红色的"This is red"。
And if we execute this line ,we get a red "This is red".
你可能已经注意到了，我们这里有一个"255;0;0"，
And you might have picked up on the fact that we have a "255;0;0" here,
这只是告诉终端我们想要的颜色的RGB值。
this is just telling the RGB values of the color we want in the terminal.
你几乎可以在你任何的代码中做到这一点，
And you pretty much can do this in any piece of code that you have,
这样你就可以给输出编码颜色了。
and like that you can color code the output.
你的终端相当花哨，并支持输出许多不同的颜色。
Your terminal is fairly fancy and supports a lot of different colors in the output.
这还不是全部，只有十六分之一。
This is not even all of them, this is like a sixteenth of them.
我认为了解这个可能非常有用。
I think it can be fairly useful to know about that.
另一个问题是，也许你不喜欢或者觉得日志不适合你。
Another thing is maybe you don't enjoy or you don't think logs are really fit for you.
但问题是，许多其他系统可能会使用日志。
The thing is a lot of other systems that you might start using will use logs.
随着你构建越来越大的系统，你可能会依赖于其他依赖项。
As you start building larger and larger systems,you might rely on other dependencies.
常见的依赖项可能是Web服务器或数据库，这是非常常见的。
Common dependencies might be web servers or databases, it's a really common one.
它们会在自己的日志中记录它们的错误或异常。
And those will be logging their errors or exceptions in their own logs.
当然，你会收到一些客户端错误，
Of course, you will get some client-side error,
但有时候这些错误信息并不足以让你弄清楚发生了什么。
but those sometimes are not informative enough for you to figure out what is going on.
在大多数UNIX系统中，日志通常放在一个名为"/var/log"的文件夹下，
In most UNIX systems, the logs are usually placed under a folder called "/var/log"
如果我们列出它，我们就可以看到这里有很多日志。
and if we list it, we can see there's a bunch of logs in here.
所以我们有像关机监视器日志或一些周报告，
So we have like the shutdown monitor log, or some weekly logs.
例如与Wi-Fi相关的事情。
Things related to the Wi-Fi, for example.
如果我们输出系统日志，其中包含了很多关于系统的信息，
And if we output the System log, which contains a lot of information about the system,
我们就可以得到关于正在发生的事情的信息。
we can get information about what's going on.
同样，有一些工具可以让你更好地查看这个输出。
Similarly, there are tools that will let you more sanely go through this output.
但是在这里，我可以查看系统日志，并说：
But here, looking at the system log,I can look at this and say:
哦，有一些服务以异常代码退出了，基于这些信息，
oh there's some service that is exiting with some abnormal codeand based on that information,
我可以去尝试弄清楚发生了什么，发生了什么错误。
I can go and try to figure out what's going on,like what's going wrong.
当你使用日志时需要知道的一件事是，
One thing to know when you're working with logs is that
更传统的是，每个软件都有自己的日志，
more traditionally, every software had their own log,
比起过去，现在越来越流行将所有日志放入统一的系统日志中。
but it has been increasingly more popular to have a unified system log where everything is placed.
几乎任何应用程序都可以记录进系统日志，
Pretty much any application can log into the system log,
但它们不是以普通文本格式存储，
but instead of being in a plain text format,
而是以某种特殊格式进行压缩。
it will be compressed in some special format.
我们在数据整理讲座中就讲到过一个例子，
An example of this, it was what we covered in the data wrangling lecture.
那就是我们使用的 "journalctl"，
In the data wrangling lecture we were using the "journalctl",
它可以访问日志并输出所有输出。
which is accessing the log and outputting all that output.
在Mac上，现在使用的命令是 "log show"，它会显示大量信息。
Here in Mac, now the command is "log show", which will display a lot of information.
我只会显示最近的十秒钟，因为日志非常冗长，
I'm gonna just display the last ten seconds, because logs are really, really verbose and
仅仅显示最近10秒钟仍然会输出相当大量的行。
just displaying the last 10 seconds is still gonna output a fairly large amount of lines.
如果我们回顾一下正在发生的事情，
So if we go back through what's going on,
我们会发现有很多苹果产品正在运行，因为这是一台MacBook。
we here see that a lot of Apple things are going on, since this is a macbook.
也许我们能在这里找到一些关于系统问题的错误。
Maybe we could find errors about like some system issue here.
再说一遍，它们相当冗长，所以你可能需要练习你的数据整理技巧，
Again they're fairly verbose, so you might want to practice your data wrangling techniques here,
例如10秒钟相当于大约500行日志，
like 10 seconds equal to like 500 lines of logs,
所以你可以大概知道每秒钟有多少行。
so you can kind of get an idea of how many lines per second you're getting.
它们不仅可以用于解析其他程序的输出，
They're not only useful for figuring out some other programs' output, they're also useful for you,
也可以用于您自己的日志记录。(是否有问题？)
if you want to log there instead of into your own file.
因此，使用 "logger" 命令，在Linux和Mac中，
So using the "logger" command, in both linux and mac,
您可以说，好的，我要将 "Hello Logs" 记录在此系统日志中。
You can say okay I'm gonna log this "Hello Logs" into this system log.
我们执行该命令，然后可以通过查看最近一分钟的日志来检查，
We execute the command and then we can check by going through the last minute of logs,
因为它会非常近，然后通过grep搜索 "Hello" 来找到我们的条目。
since it's gonna be fairly recent, and grepping for that "Hello" we find our entry.
我们发现最近创建的条目，显示了 "Hello Logs"。
Fairly recent entry, that we just created that said "Hello Logs".
随着您越来越熟悉这些工具，
As you become more and more familiar with these tools,
您会发现自己越来越经常使用日志，
you will find yourself using the logs more and more often,
因为即使您有一些错误，
since even if you have some bug that you haven't detected,
而且程序已经运行了一段时间，
and the program has been running for a while,
也许信息已经在日志中，
maybe the information is already in the log
可以告诉您足够的信息来找出问题所在。
and can tell you enough to figure out what is going on.
然而，printf调试并不是万能的。
However, printf debugging is not everything.
现在我要介绍调试器。
So now I'm going to be covering debuggers.
但首先，有关日志的任何问题吗？
But first any questions on logs so far?
那么您可以从日志中了解到什么样的信息？
So what kind of things can you figure out from the logs?
像这个 "Hello Logs" 就表明在那个时间你执行了一些关于Hello的操作吗？
like this Hello Logs says that you did something with Hello at that time?
是的，例如，我可以编写一个Bash脚本来检测...
Yeah, like say, for example, I can write a bash script that detects...
每次检查我连接到哪个Wi-Fi网络。
Well, that checks every time what Wi-Fi network I'm connected to.
每次它检测到网络已更改，
And every time it detects that it has changed,
它就会在日志中创建一个条目，并说：
it makes an entry in the logs and says
哦，现在看起来我们已经更换了Wi-Fi网络。
Oh now it looks like we have changed Wi-Fi networks.
然后你可以回过头来解析日志，比如：
and then you might go back and parse through the logs and take like, okay
“好的，我的电脑是何时从一个Wi-Fi网络切换到另一个网络的？”
When did my computer change from one Wi-Fi network to another.
这只是一个简单的例子，
And this is just kind of a simple example
但这里有许多许多类型的信息可以被记录。
But there are many, many ways, many types of information that you could be logging here.
更普遍的情况是，
More commonly, you will probably want to check if your computer, for example, is
你可能想要检查你的电脑是否因为某些未知原因进入了睡眠状态，比如它处于休眠模式。
entering sleep, for example, for some unknown reason. Like it's on hibernation mode.
日志中可能有一些信息说明是
There's probably some information in the logs about
谁要求它进入睡眠状态，或者为什么会发生这种情况。
who asked that to happen, or why it's that happening.
还有其他问题吗？好的。
Any other questions? Okay.
所以当printf调试不够用时，
So when printf debugging is not enough,
最好的替代方法是使用……
the best alternative after that is using...
（退出）
[Exit that]
使用调试器。
So, it's using a debugger.
调试器是一种工具，它将包装你的代码并让你运行代码，
So a debugger is a tool that will wrap around your code and will let you run your code,
但它会对其进行控制。
but it will kind of keep control over it.
因此，它将允许你逐步执行代码并设置断点。
So it will let you step through the code and execute it and set breakpoints.
如果你曾经使用过类似IDE这样的工具，
You probably have seen debuggers in some way,
你可能已经以某种方式看到过调试器，因为IDE具有这种花哨的功能：
if you have ever used something like an IDE, because IDEs have this kind of fancy:
在这里设置断点，执行……
set a breakpoint here, execute, ...
但是归根结底，这些工具使用的
But at the end of the day what these tools are using is
只是命令行调试器，
just these command line debuggers
并且它们只是以一种非常花哨的格式呈现它们。
and they're just presenting them in a really fancy format.
在这里，我们有一个完全损坏的冒泡排序算法。
Here we have a completely broken bubble sort, a simple sorting algorithm.
不用担心细节，
Don't worry about the details,
但我们只是想要对这里的数组进行排序。
but we just want to sort this array that we have here.
我们可以尝试通过执行Python bubble.py来做到这一点。
We can try doing that by just doing Python bubble.py
当我们这样做时……
And when we do that...
哦，出现了一些索引错误，列表索引超出范围。
Oh there's some index error, list index out of range.
我们可以开始添加打印输出，
We could start adding prints
但如果字符串很长，我们可能会得到很多信息。
but if have a really long string, we can get a lot of information.
那么，我们如何回到崩溃时刻呢？
So how about we go up to the moment that we crashed?
我们可以回到那个时刻并检查程序的当前状态。
We can go to that moment and examine what the current state of the program was.
所以，为了做到这一点，我将使用Python调试器来运行程序。
So for doing that I'm gonna run the program using the Python debugger.
在这里，我技术上使用的是ipython调试器，
Here I'm using technically the ipython debugger,
因为它具有漂亮的语法着色，
just because it has nice coloring syntax
所以对于我们两个来说更容易理解输出中正在发生的事情。
so it's probably easier for both of us to understand what's going on in the output.
但它们基本上是相同的。
But they're pretty much identical anyway.
我们执行这个，现在我们得到一个提示，
So we execute this, and now we are given a prompt
告诉我们我们在程序的第一行。
where we're being told that we are here, at the very first line of our program.
我们可以......
And we can...
"L"代表"List"，所以和许多这样的工具一样，
"L" stands for "List", so as with many of these tools
有一种操作语言，
there's kind of like a language of operations that you can do,
它们通常是助记符，就像VIM或TMUX一样。
and they are often mnemonic, as it was the case with VIM or TMUX.
所以在这里，“L”是为了“列出”代码，我们可以看到整个代码。
So here, "L" is for "Listing" the code,  and we can see the entire code.
"S"代表"Step"，它可以让我们逐行执行代码。
"S" is for "Step" and will let us kind of one line at a time, go through the execution.
问题是，我们只有在某段时间后才会触发错误。
The thing is we're only triggering the error some time later.
所以我们可以重新启动程序，而不是尝试一步步走到错误处，
So we can restart the program and instead of trying to step until we get to the issue,
我们可以只要求程序继续运行，即“C”命令，然后我们就到了问题所在。
we can just ask for the program to continue which is the "C" command and
我们到达了这一行，一切都崩溃了，
hey, we reached the issue. We got to this line where everything crashed,
我们得到了这个“list index out of range”错误。
we're getting this list index out of range.
现在我们可以说，嗯？
And now that we are here we can say, huh?
好的，首先，让我们打印数组的值。这是当前数组的值，
Okay, first, let's print the value of the array. This is the value of the current array
所以我们有六个项。好的。
So we have six items. Okay.
这里“J”的值是多少？
What is the value of "J" here?
所以我们查看“J”的值。“J”在这里是5，这将是最后一个元素，
So we look at the value of "J". "J" is 5 here, which will be the last element,
但“J”加1将是6，所以这触发了越界错误。
but "J" plus 1 is going to be 6, so that's triggering the out of bounds error.
所以我们要做的是，这个“N”，不是“N”，而是“N减1”。
So what we have to do is this "N", instead of "N" has to be "N minus one".
我们已经确定错误出现在这里。
We have identified that the error lies there.
所以我们可以退出，也就是“Q”。
So we can quit, which is "Q".
再次，因为它是一个事后调试器。
Again, because it's a post-mortem debugger.
我们回到代码并说好的，
We go back to the code and say okay,
我们需要添加这个“N减1”。
we need to append this "N minus one".
这将防止列表索引超出范围，
That will prevent the list index out of range and
如果我们再次运行此代码而不使用调试器，好的，现在没有错误了。
if we run this again without the debugger, okay, no errors now.
但是这不是我们排序后的列表。
But this is not our sorted list.
这是排序的，但不是我们的列表。
This is sorted, but it's not our list.
我们缺少列表中的某些条目，
We are missing entries from our list,
所以我们在这里遇到了一些行为问题。
so there is some behavioral issue that we're reaching here.
再次，我们可以开始使用printf调试，但现在有一种预感，
Again, we could start using printf debugging but kind of a hunch now is
但现在有一种预感，可能我们在冒泡排序程序中交换条目的方式是错误的。
that probably the way we're swapping entries in the bubble sort program is wrong.
我们可以使用调试器来解决这个问题。
We can use the debugger for this.
我们可以逐步进行交换操作，
We can go through them to the moment we're doing a swap
并检查交换是如何执行的。
and check how the swap is being performed.
简单概述一下，我们有两个for循环，在最嵌套的循环中，
So a quick overview, we have two for loops and in the most nested loop,
我们检查数组是否大于另一个数组。
we are checking if the array is larger than the other array.
问题是，如果我们只试图执行到这一行，
The thing is if we just try to execute until this line,
它只会在我们进行交换时触发。
it's only going to trigger whenever we make a swap.
所以我们可以在第六行设置一个断点。
So what we can do is we can set a breakpoint in the sixth line.
我们可以在这一行创建一个断点，
We can create a breakpoint in this line and then the program will execute
程序执行到尝试交换变量时，程序就会停止。
and the moment we try to swap variables is when the program is going to stop.
所以我们在那里创建一个断点，然后继续执行程序。
So we create a breakpoint there and then we continue the execution of the program.
程序停止，并说“嘿，我已经执行并到达这一行了”。
The program halts and says hey, I have executed and I have reached this line.
现在我们可以使用“locals()”函数，
Now I can use "locals()", which is a Python function
它返回一个包含所有值的字典，以便快速查看整个上下文。
that returns a dictionary with all the values to quickly see the entire context.
字符串和数组都没问题，而且数组有6个元素，这只是一个开端。
The string, the array is fine and is six, again, just the beginning and
我继续执行下一行，哦，我找到了问题：
I step, go to the next line. Oh, and I identify the issue:
我只交换了一个变量，而不是同时交换，
I'm swapping one item at a time, instead of simultaneously,
这就是我们逐渐丢失变量的原因。
so that's what's triggering the fact that we're losing variables as we go through.
这只是一个非常简单的例子，
That's kind of a very simple example,
但调试器非常强大。
but debuggers are really powerful.
大多数编程语言都提供一些调试器，
Most programming languages will give you some sort of debugger,
当你进行更低级别的调试时，你可能会遇到像GDB这样的工具。
and when you go to more low level debugging you might run into tools like...
你可能想使用类似于GDB这样的工具。
You might want to use something like GDB.
GDB非常适用于C/C++和所有这些类似C的语言。
And GDB has one nice property: GDB works really well with C/C++ and all these C-like languages.
但是GDB实际上可以让您使用几乎任何可执行的二进制文件。
But GDB actually lets you work with pretty much any binary that you can execute.
例如，在这里，我们有一个sleep程序，
So for example here we have sleep,
它只是一个将休眠20秒的程序。
which is just a program that's going to sleep for 20 seconds.
它被加载，然后我们可以运行它，
It's loaded and then we can do run,
并通过发送中断信号来中断它。
and then we can interrupt this sending an interrupt signal.
GDB正在为我们显示程序中发生的非常低级别的信息。
And GDB is displaying for us, here, very low-level information about what's going on in the program.
因此，我们正在获取堆栈跟踪，我们可以看到我们在这个nanosleep函数中，
So we're getting the stack trace, we're seeing we are in this nanosleep function,
我们可以看到机器上所有硬件寄存器的值。
we can see the values of all the hardware registers in your machine.
因此，您可以使用这些工具获取许多低级别的详细信息。
So you can get a lot of low-level detail using these tools.
我想这就是我想介绍调试器的所有内容了。是否有相关的问题？
I think that's all I want to cover for debuggers. Any questions related to that?
调试时另一个有趣的工具是，
Another interesting tool when you're trying to debug is that
有时您想调试的方式就像您的程序是一个黑盒子。
sometimes you want to debug as if your program is a black box.
因此，您可能知道程序的内部，
So you, maybe, know what the internals of the program
但同时，您的计算机也知道程序何时尝试执行某些操作。
but at the same time your computer knows whenever your program is trying to do some operations.
因此，在UNIX系统中，有这样一个概念，即用户级代码和内核级代码。
So this is in UNIX systems, there's this notion of like user level code and kernel level code.
当您尝试执行一些操作，例如读取文件或读取网络连接时，
And when you try to do some operations like reading a file or like reading the network connection
您将不得不执行称为系统调用的操作。
you will have to do something called system calls.
你可以获取一个程序并查看其操作,
You can get a program and go through those operations
询问此软件执行了哪些操作？
and ask what operations did this software do?
例如，如果你有一个只应执行数学运算的Python函数，
So for example, if you have like a Python function
并将其运行通过此程序，
that is only supposed to do a mathematical operation and you run it through this program,
却发现它实际上在读取文件，
and it's actually reading files,
这是为什么？
Why is it reading files?
它不应该读取文件。
It shouldn't be reading files.
那么，
So, let's see.
我们可以使用"strace"这个工具。
This is "strace".
例如，我们可以这样做。
So for example, we can do it something like this.
我们将运行"LS - L"命令，
So here we're gonna run the "LS - L"
忽略LS的输出，
And then we're ignoring the output of LS,
但不忽略STRACE的输出。
but we are not ignoring the output of STRACE.
如果我们执行它，
So if we execute that...
我们将得到大量输出。
We're gonna get a lot of output.
这是所有不同系统调用，
This is all the different system calls
这个LS命令已执行的调用。
That this LS has executed.
你会看到很多OPEN调用，你会看到FSTAT。
You will see a bunch of OPEN, you will see FSTAT.
例如，因为它必须列出在此文件夹中的所有文件的属性，
And for example, since it has to list all the properties of the files that are in this folder,
我们可以检查LSTAT调用。
we can check for the LSTAT call.
因此，LSTAT调用将检查文件的属性，
So the LSTAT call will check for the properties of the files
我们可以看到，实际上所有在此目录中的文件和文件夹
and we can see that, effectively, all the files and folders that are in this directory
都是通过LS系统调用进行访问的。
have been accessed through a system call, through LS.
有趣的是，有时你实际上不需要运行代码
Interestingly, sometimes you actually don't need to run your code to figure out
就可以找出代码中的问题。
that there is something wrong with your code.
到目前为止，我们已经看到了足够多的通过运行代码来识别问题的方式，
So far we have seen enough ways of identifying issues by running the code,
但如果
but what if you...
你像这个屏幕上显示的代码一样看着一段代码，
you can look at a piece of code like this,
你也可以找到一个问题。
like the one I have shown right now in this screen,and identify an issue.
例如，这里我们有一些非常愚蠢的代码。
So for example here, we have some really silly piece of code.
它定义了一个函数，打印几个变量，乘以一些变量，
It defines a function, prints a few variables,multiplies some variables,
然后等待一段时间，然后我们尝试打印BAZ。
it sleeps for a while and then we try to print BAZ.
你可以试着看这个代码，然后说，“BAZ从未在任何地方定义过。
And you could try to look at this and say, hey, BAZ has never been defined anywhere.
这是一个新的变量。
This is a new variable.
你可能想说BAR但你打错了。
You probably meant to say BAR,but you just mistyped it.
问题是，如果我们尝试运行此程序，
Thing is,  if we try to run this program,
它将需要60秒，因为我们必须等待time.sleep函数完成。
it's gonna take 60 seconds, because like we have to wait until this time.sleep function finishes.
这里，time.sleep() 只是为了示例而已，
Here, sleep is just for motivating the example
但通常你可能会加载一个数据集，
but in general you may be loading a data set that takes really long
因为需要将所有数据复制到内存中而需要很长时间。
because you have to copy everything into memory.
事实上，有些程序会将源代码作为输入，
And the thing is, there are programs that will take source code as input,
对其进行处理，并指出代码的哪些部分可能是错误的。
will process it and will say, oh probably this is wrong about this piece of code.
在Python或一般情况下，这些被称为静态分析工具。
So in Python,or in general, these are called static analysis tools.
在Python中，例如pyflakes。
In Python we have for example pyflakes.
如果我们将这段代码输入pyflakes中，
If we get this piece of code and run it through pyflakes,
pyflakes会给我们指出两个问题。第一个问题是......
pyflakes is gonna give us a couple of issues. First one is the one....
第二个问题是我们已经指出的：这里有一个未定义的变量名叫做BAZ。
The second one is the one we identified: here's an undefined name called BAZ.
你可能需要对此进行处理。
You probably should be doing something about that.
另一个问题是：你正在重定义那一行中的FOO变量名。
And the other one is like oh, you're redefining the FOO variable name in that line.
所以，这里我们定义了一个FOO函数，
So here we have a FOO function and then we are kind of
然后我们通过使用一个循环变量来掩盖该函数。
shadowing that function by using a loop variable here.
现在我们定义的那个FOO函数已经不可访问了，
So now that FOO function that we defined is not accessible anymore
如果我们之后尝试调用它，就会出现错误。
and then if we try to call it afterwards, we will get into errors.
还有其他类型的静态分析工具。
There are other types of Static Analysis tools.
MYPY是另一个不同的工具。
MYPY is a different one.
MYPY会报告相同的两个错误，
MYPY is gonna report the same two errors,
但它也会抱怨类型检查。
but it's also going to complain about type checking.
它会说，这里你正在将一个整数乘以一个浮点数，
So it's gonna say, oh here you're multiplying an int by a float and
如果你关心代码的类型检查，你不应该混淆它们。
if you care about the type checking of your code,  you should not be mixing those up.
这可能有点不方便，需要运行这个工具，
it can be kind of inconvenient, having to run this,
查看出错的行，然后回到你的VIM或编辑器中，
look at the line, going back to your VIM or like your editor,
找出这个错误的位置。
and figuring out what the error matches to.
已经有解决方案了。
There are already solutions for that.
一种方法是将大多数编辑器与这些工具集成在一起，这里...
One way is that you can integrate most editors with these tools and here..
你可以看到bash上有一些红色的高亮，
You can see there is like some red highlighting on the bash,
它会读取这里的最后一行。
and it will read the last line here.
未定义的变量 'baz'。
So, undefined named 'baz'.
所以，当我编辑这段Python代码时，
So as I'm editing this piece of Python code,
我的编辑器会给我反馈，告诉我这里有什么问题。
my editor is gonna give me feedback about what's going wrong with this.
或者，这里有另外一个问题，说你正在重新定义未使用的foo。
Or like here have another one saying the redefinition of unused foo.
甚至，有些投诉是关于代码的风格。
And even, there are some stylistic complaints.
例如，我期望有两个空行。
So, oh, I will expect two empty lines.
在Python中，函数定义之间应该有两行空行。
So like in Python, you should be having two empty lines between a function definition.
emmm.....
There are...
有一个关于很多
there is a resource on the lecture notes about
不同编程语言的静态分析工具的课程笔记资源。
pretty much static analyzers for a lot of different programming languages.
甚至还有针对英语的静态分析工具。
There are even static analyzers for English.
我有这门课的笔记，
So I have my notes for the class here,
在这个英语静态分析工具“writegood”中运行，
and if I run it through this static analyzer for English, that is "writegood".
它会抱怨一些风格上的问题。
It's going to complain about some stylistic properties.
例如，“very”是一个模糊的词汇，我不应该使用它，
So like, oh, I'm using "very", which is a weasel word and I shouldn't be using it.
“quickly”也会削弱含义。
Or "quickly" can weaken meaning,
你可以用它来检查拼写错误或进行很多不同类型的风格分析。
and you can have this for spell checking, or for a lot of different types of stylistic analysis.
目前有什么问题吗？
Any questions so far?
哦，我忘了提到......
Oh, I forgot to mention...
根据你正在执行的任务，将有不同类型的调试器可用。
Depending on the task that you're performing, there will be different types of debuggers.
例如，如果你在进行Web开发，
For example, if you're doing web development,
Firefox和Chrome都有非常好的用于调试网站的工具集。
both Firefox and Chrome have a really really good set of tools for doing debugging for websites.
所以，我们在这里进行元素检查，我们可以得到......
So here we go and say inspect element, we can get the...
你知道吗？
do you know?
如何让这个更大......
how to make this larger...
我们获取了这门课网页的整个源代码。
We're getting the entire source code for the web page for the class.
哦，是的，
Oh, yeah, here we go.
这个好了吗？
Is that better?
现在我们可以实际上更改有关课程的属性。
And we can actually go and change properties about the course.
我们可以编辑标题。
So we can say... we can edit the title.
这不是一个关于调试和分析性能的课程。
Say, this is not a class on debugging and profiling.
现在网站的代码已经改变了。
And now the code for the website has changed.
这就是为什么你永远不应该相信任何网站的截图的原因之一，
This is one of the reasons why you should never trust any screenshots of websites,
因为它们可能被完全修改。
because they can be completely modified.
你还可以修改这个样式。
And you can also modify this style.
例如，这里我使用了深色模式首选项，但我们可以改变它。
Like, here I have things using the dark mode preference, but we can alter that.
因为在最后一天，浏览器是为我们渲染这个网站的。
Because at the end of the day, the browser is rendering this for us.
我们可以检查cookie，但有很多不同的操作。
We can check the cookies, but there's like a lot of different operations.
JavaScript还有一个内置的调试器，因此你可以逐步调试JavaScript代码。
There's also a built-in debugger for JavaScript, so you can step through JavaScript code.
因此，总结一下，取决于你正在做什么，
So kind of the takeaway is, depending on what you are doing,
你可能需要搜索程序员为自己构建的工具。
you will probably want to search for what tools programmers have built for them.
现在我要转换话题，不再谈论调试，
Now I'm gonna switch gears and stop talking about debugging,
也就是找到代码中的问题，
which is kind of finding issues with the code, right?
或者说表现
kind of more about the behavior,
而是开始谈论如何使用性能分析。
and then start talking about like how you can use profiling.
性能分析可以帮助你优化代码，
And profiling is how to optimize the code.
可能是因为你想优化CPU、内存、网络等方面的性能。
It might be because you want to optimize the CPU, the memory, the network, ...
有许多不同的原因需要进行优化。
There are many different reasons that you want to be optimizing it.
就像调试一样，
As it was the case with debugging, the kind of first-order approach
很多人有的第一种方法是使用
that a lot of people have experience with already is
printf进行性能分析，例如...
oh, let's use just printf profiling, so to say, like we can just take...
我把这个放大点
Let me make this larger.
我们可以记录当前时间，
We can take the current time here,
然后执行一些操作，
then we can check, we can do some execution
再记录时间并从原始时间中减去它。
and then we can take the time again and subtract it from the original time.
这样你就可以缩小范围，
And by doing this you can kind of narrow down
并屏蔽代码的某些不同部分
and fence some different parts of your code
分析不同部分代码之间的时间差。
and try to figure out what is the time taken between those two parts.
这很好。但有时结果可能会有点意外。
And that's good. But sometimes it can be interesting, the results.
例如，这里我们sleep了0.5秒，输出结果显示是
So here, we're sleeping for 0.5 seconds and the output is saying,
0.5加上一些额外的时间，这很有趣。
oh it's 0.5 plus some extra time,which is kind of interesting.
如果我们继续运行它，我们会发现一些小的误差。
And if we keep running it, we see there's like some small error and the thing is
事实上，我们正在测量的是通常被称为“实际时间”的时间。
here, what we're actually measuring is what is usually referred to as the "real time".
实际时间就像你拿着一只钟表，
Real time is as if you get like a clock,
在程序开始时启动，
and you start it when your program starts,
程序结束时停止。
and you stop it when your program ends.
但问题是，在你的计算机中，不仅仅是你的程序在运行。
But the thing is, in your computer it is not only your program that is running.
还有许多其他程序同时在运行，
There are many other programs running at the same time
可能是那些正在占用CPU的程序。
and those might be the ones that are taking the CPU.
因此，为了理解这一点，
So, to try to make sense of that,
有很多，emmm...
A lot of...
你会发现很多程序使用的术语是
you'll see a lot of programs using the terminology
实际时间、用户时间和系统时间。
that is real time, user time and system time.
实际时间就是我解释的整个时间长度，从开始到结束。
Real time is what I explained, which is kind of the entire length of time from start to finish.
然后有用户时间，这是你的程序在CPU上执行用户级别周期所花费的时间。
Then there is the user time, which is the amount of time your program \N spent on the CPU doing user level cycles.
正如我提到的，在UNIX中，
So as I was mentioning, in UNIX,
你可以运行用户级别代码或内核级别代码。
you can be running user level code or kernel level code.
系统时间则是相反的，它是你的程序在CPU上
System is kind of the opposite, it's the amount of CPU,
执行内核模式指令所花费的时间。
like the amount of time that your program spent on the CPU executing kernel mode instructions.
让我们通过一个示例来展示。
So let's show this with an example.
这里我要使用一个名为"time"的命令，
Here I'm going to "time", which is a command,
它将为以下命令获取这三个指标，
a shell command that's gonna get these three metrics for the following command,
然后我只是从一个托管在西班牙的网站中获取一个URL。
and then I'm just grabbing a URL from a website that is hosted in Spain.
因此，这将需要一些额外的时间来去那里并返回。
So that's gonna take some extra time to go over there and then go back.
如果我们看到，这里，
If we see, here,
如果...
if we were to just...
在程序的开头和结尾之间有两个打印语句。
We have two prints, between the beginning and the end of the program.
我们可能会认为这个程序需要大约600毫秒才能执行，
We could think that this program is taking like 600 milliseconds to execute,
但实际上大部分时间都花在等待网络响应上，
but actually most of that time was spent just waiting for the response on the other side of the network
而我们实际上只花了16毫秒的用户级别
and we actually only spent 16 milliseconds at the user level
和9秒的总时间，实际上执行了CURL代码的时间只有25毫秒，
and like 9 seconds, in total 25 milliseconds, actually executing CURL code.
其他都是在等待。
Everything else was just waiting.
有关计时的任何问题吗？
Any questions related to timing?
好的，所以计时可能会变得棘手，这也是一种黑匣子解决方案。
Ok, so timing can be can become tricky, it's also kind of a black box solution.
或者如果您开始添加打印语句，
Or if you start adding print statements,
那么到处都是打印语句会变得很难。
it's kind of hard to add print statements, with time everywhere.
所以程序员已经找到了更好的工具。
So programmers have figured out better tools.
这些通常称为"分析器"。
These are usually referred to as "profilers".
我要快速提醒一下的是，
One quick note that I'm gonna make, is that
分析器通常是指CPU分析器，
profilers, like usually when people refer to profilers they usually talk about CPU profilers
因为它们是最常见的，可以确定CPU上花费时间的位置。
because they are the most common, at identifying where like time is being spent on the CPU.
分析器通常有两种类型：
Profilers usually come in kind of two flavors:
跟踪分析器和采样分析器。
there's tracing profilers and sampling profilers.
知道它们之间的区别很好，因为输出可能会不同。
and it's kind of good to know the difference because the output might be different.
跟踪分析器会对您的代码进行插桩。
Tracing profilers kind of instrument your code.
所以它们会随着您的代码执行，
So they kind of execute with your code and every time your code enters a function call,
并在每次代码进入函数调用时进行记录。
they kind of take a note of it.
就像这个时刻我们正在进入这个函数调用，
It's like, oh we're entering this function call at this moment in time and
然后继续前进，一旦完成，它们可以报告
they keep going and, once they finish, they can report oh,
你在这个函数中执行了多少时间，在另一个函数中执行了多少时间，
you spent this much time executing in this function and this much time in this other function.
以此类推，这就是我们现在将要看到的例子。
So on, so forth, which is the example that we're gonna see now.
另一种类型的工具是跟踪采样分析器。
Another type of tools are tracing, sorry, sampling profilers.
跟踪分析器的问题在于它们会增加很多开销。
The issue with tracing profilers is they add a lot of overhead.
就像您可能正在运行您的代码，
Like you might be running your code and having these kind of
并且在您旁边进行这些统计分析，这将影响您程序的性能，
profiling next to you making all these counts, will hinder the performance of your program,
所以您可能会得到稍微偏差的统计数。
so you might get counts that are slightly off.
采样分析器会执行您的程序，
A sampling profiler, what it's gonna do is gonna execute your program
并在每100毫秒、10毫秒或其他定义的时间段内停止程序。
and every 100 milliseconds, 10 milliseconds, like some defined period,
它会停止程序，查看堆栈跟踪
it's gonna stop your program. It's gonna halt it,
并确定当前在层次结构中
it's gonna look at the stack trace and say, oh, you're right now in this point in the hierarchy,
同时哪个函数正在执行。
and identify which function is gonna be executing at that point.
理念是只要您足够长时间执行此操作，
The idea is that as long as you execute this for long enough,
就可以获得足够的统计数据，了解大部分时间都花在了哪里。
you're gonna get enough statistics to know where most of the time is being spent.
接下来让我们看一个跟踪分析的例子。
So, let's see an example of a tracing profiling.
这里有一段代码，
So here we have a piece of code that is just like a
它只是 Python 中 grep 的一个简单重新实现。
really simple re-implementation of grep done in Python.
我们想要检查程序的瓶颈在哪里。
What we want to check is what is the bottleneck of this program?
我们只是打开了一堆文件，试图匹配这个模式，
Like we're just opening a bunch of files,trying to match this pattern,
然后在找到匹配项时打印出来。
and then printing whenever we find a match.
可能是正则表达式，也可能是打印操作，
And maybe it's the regex, maybe it's the print...
我们不确定。
We don't really know.
为了在 Python 中执行这个操作，我们使用 "cProfile"。
So to do this in Python, we have the "cProfile".
我调用这个模块，
And here I'm just calling this module
说我想按总时间排序，
and saying I want to sort this by the total amount of time,
我们会很快看到这个。
that we're gonna see briefly.
我调用我们刚才在编辑器中看到的程序。
I'm calling the program we just saw in the editor.
我要执行这个程序一千次，
I'm gonna execute this a thousand times
然后将 grep 的参数
and then I want to match the grep Arguments here
应用于这里的所有 Python 文件。
is I want to match these regex to all the Python files in here.
这将产生一些输出，
And this is gonna output some...
然后我们将查看它。
This is gonna produce some output, then we're gonna look at it.
首先是所有 grep 的输出，
First, is all the output from the greps, but at the very end,
但最后，我们得到了分析器本身的输出。
we're getting output from the profiler itself.
如果我们向上滚动，我们可以看到，通过排序，我们可以看到总调用次数。
If we go up,we can see that, hey, by sorting we can see that the total number of calls.
因为我们执行了这个程序一千次，所以我们执行了8000次调用，
So we did 8000 calls, because we executed this 1000 times and
这是我们在这个函数中花费的总时间(累计时间)。
this is the total amount of time we spent in this function (cumulative time).
在这里，
And here we can start to identify where the bottleneck is.
这个内置方法 IO open 表示
So here, this built-in method IO open, is saying that
我们花费了大量时间等待从磁盘读取或...
we're spending a lot of the time just waiting for reading from the disk or...
在这里，我们可以检查，大量时间也花在了尝试匹配正则表达式上，
There, we can check, hey, a lot of time is also being spent trying to match the regex.
这是可以预期的。
Which is something that you will expect.
使用此追踪分析器的一个警告是，
One of the caveats of using this tracing profiler is that,
正如您可以看到的那样，我们看到了我们的函数，
as you can see, here we're seeing our function
但也看到了很多与内置函数对应的函数。
but we're also seeing a lot of functions that correspond to built-ins.
因此，像来自库的第三方函数这样的函数。
So like, functions that are third party functions from the libraries.
随着您构建越来越复杂的代码，
And as you start building more and more complex code,
这将变得更加困难。
This is gonna be much harder.
这里是另一个Python代码片段，不要阅读它，
So here is another piece of Python code that, don't read through it,
它只是获取课程网站，
what it's doing is just grabbing the course website and then it's printing all the...
然后打印出所有的超链接。
It's parsing it, and then it's printing all the hyperlinks that it has found.
因此有这两个操作：
So there are like these two operations:
前往该网站，获取并解析它，然后打印链接。
going there, grabbing a website, and then parsing it, printing the links.
我们可能想要了解
And we might want to get a sense of
这两个操作之间的比较。
how those two operations compare to each other.
如果我们尝试执行cProfiler，我们将执行相同的操作，
If we just try to execute the cProfiler here and we're gonna do the same,
这不会打印任何内容。
this is not gonna print anything.
我正在使用到目前为止我们没有见过的一个工具，但我认为它很好。
I'm using a tool we haven't seen so far,but I think it's pretty nice.
它是"TAC"，是"CAT"的反向，
It's "TAC", which is the opposite of "CAT",
并且会反转输出，因此我不必上下查看。
and it is going to reverse the output so I don't have to go up and look.
我们这样做，
So we do this and...
嘿，我们得到了一些有趣的输出。
Hey, we get some interesting output.
我们在这个内置方法socket_getaddr_info、_imp_create_dynamic和
we're spending a bunch of time in this built-in method socket_getaddr_info
method_connect中花费了大量的时间以及posix_stat…，
and like in _imp_create_dynamic and method_connect and posix_stat...
我的代码中没有直接调用这些函数，
nothing in my code is directly calling these functions so I don't really know
因此我不知道发出Web请求
what is the split between the operation of making a web request
和解析该Web请求的输出之间的拆分是什么。
and parsing the output of that web request.
因此，我们可以
So, for that, we can use
使用不同类型的分析器，即行分析器。
a different type of profiler which is a line profiler.
行分析器只会以更易读的方式呈现相同的结果，
And the line profiler is just going to present the same results
即对于此代码行，
but in a more human-readable way,
这是花费的时间。
which is just, for this line of code, this is the amount of time things took.
因此，我们必须向Python函数添加一个装饰器来完成这项工作。
So it knows it has to do that, we have to add a decorator to the Python function, we do that.
当我们这样做时，我们现在获得了略微裁剪的输出，
And as we do that, we now get slightly cropped output,
但主要思路是我们可以查看时间百分比，
but the main idea, we can look at the percentage of time
并且我们可以看到进行此请求、
and we can see that making this request,
获取操作所花费的时间占总时间的88%，而解析响应所花费的时间仅占10.9%。
get operation, took 88% of the time, whereas parsing the response took only 10.9% of the time.
这可能非常有信息量，
This can be really informative
许多不同的编程语言都将支持这种类型的行分析。
and a lot of different programming languages will support this type of a line profiling.
有时你可能不关心 CPU 的性能，
Sometimes, you might not care about CPU.
也许你关心内存或其他资源。
Maybe you care about the memory or like some other resource.
同样地，也有内存分析器：在 Python 中
Similarly, there are memory profilers: in Python
有 "memory_profiler"，在 C 中有 "Valgrind"。
there is "memory_profiler", for C you will have "Valgrind".
这里是一个相当简单的例子，
So here is a fairly simple example,
我们只是创建了一个包含一百万个元素的列表。
we just create this list with a million elements.
这将占用大约几兆字节的空间，
That's going to consume like megabytes of space and
并且我们做同样的事情，创建另一个包含两千万个元素的列表。
we do the same, creating another one with 20 million elements.
为了检查内存分配是多少？
To check, what was the memory allocation?
它将如何发生，消耗量是多少？
How it's gonna happen, what's the consumption?
我们可以使用一个内存分析器来执行它，
We can go through one memory profiler and we execute it,
并告诉我们总内存使用量和增量。
and it's telling us the total memory usage and the increments.
我们可以看到一些开销，
And we can see that we have some overhead,
因为这是一种解释性语言，当我们创建一个包含一百万条条目的列表时，
because this is an interpreted language and when we create this million,
我们将需要这么多兆字节的信息。
this list with a million entries, we're gonna need this many megabytes of information.
然后我们又得到了另外 150 兆字节。
Then we were getting another 150 megabytes.
接下来，我们释放了这个条目，总量就减少了。
Then, we're freeing this entry and that's decreasing the total amount.
我们没有因为错误而得到负增量，可能是在分析器中出现了 bug。
We are not getting a negative increment because of a bug, probably in the profiler.
但是，如果你知道你的程序占用了大量内存，
But if you know that your program is taking a huge amount of memory
而你不知道为什么，可能是因为你在复制对象，
and you don't know why, maybe because you're copying
而不是应该在原地进行操作，
objects where you should be doing things in place,
那么使用内存分析器就可以非常有用。
then using a memory profiler can be really useful.
实际上，有一个练习将带领你完成这个操作，
And in fact there's an exercise that will kind of work you through that,
比较就地排序的版本和不是就地排序的版本，
comparing an in-place version of quicksort with like a non-inplace,
后者会不断制作新的副本。
that keeps making new and new copies.
如果你使用内存分析器，
And if you using the memory profiler
你可以得到两者之间的很好的比较。
you can get a really good comparison between the two of them
有没有关于分析的问题？
Any questions so far, with profiling?
内存分析器是在运行程序以获得结果吗？
Is the memory profiler running the program in order to get that?
是的……你可能能够通过查看代码来弄清楚。
Yeah... you might be able to figure out like just looking at the code.
但是随着程序越来越复杂，这就不是那么容易了（至少对于这个代码而言）。
But as you get more and more complex (for this code at least)
这个工具会运行程序，
But you get more and more complex programs what this is doing is running through the program
并在每一行开始时查看堆，然后说
and for every line, at the very beginning, it's looking at the heap and saying
“我现在分配了哪些对象？
"What are the objects that I have allocated now?"
我有七兆字节的对象”，
"I have seven megabytes of objects",
然后再到下一行，再次查看，
and then goes to the next line,looks again,
“噢，现在我有 50 兆字节，所以我现在增加了 43 个”。
"Oh now I have 50, so I have now added 43 there".
你可以在代码中要求这些操作的每一行自己完成这个操作，
Again, you could do this yourself by asking for those operations in your code, every single line.
但这不是你应该做的，
But that's not how you should be doing things
因为别人已经为你编写了这些工具。
since people have already written these tools for you to use.
正如 strace 的情况一样，
As it was the case with...
你可以在分析中做类似的事情。
So as in the case with strace, you can do something similar in profiling.
也许你不关心具体的代码行，
You might not care about the specific lines of code that you have,
但是你想检查外部事件。
but maybe you want to check for outside events.
你可能想检查你的计算机程序使用了多少CPU周期，
Like, you maybe want to check how many CPU cycles your computer program is using,
或者它创建了多少页面错误。
or how many page faults it's creating.
也许你的缓存位置很差，这些问题会以某种方式表现出来。
Maybe you have like bad cache locality and that's being manifested somehow.
为此，有一个“perf”命令。
So for that, there is the "perf" command.
perf命令会运行你的程序，
The perf command is gonna do this, where it is gonna run your program
并跟踪所有这些统计数据，并将它们反馈给你。
and it's gonna keep track of all these statistics and report them back to you.
如果你在低层级工作，这将非常有帮助。
And this can be really helpful if you are working at a lower level.
我们执行此命令，我将简要解释它在做什么。
So we execute this command, I'm gonna explain briefly what it's doing.
stress程序只是在CPU中运行，
And this stress program is just running in the CPU,
它只是一个程序，用于独占一个CPU，并测试您是否可以独占CPU。
and it's just a program to just hog one CPU and like test that you can hog the CPU.
现在，如果我们Ctrl-C，我们可以返回并获取有关页面错误数量
And now if we Ctrl-C,we can go back and we get some information about the number of page faults
或我们的代码使用的CPU周期的一些信息。
that we have or the number of CPU cycles that we utilize,
或是其它的有效信息
and other useful metrics from our code.
对于某些程序，你可以查看正在使用的函数。
For some programs you can look at what the functions that were being used were.
因此，我们可以记录此程序正在执行的操作，
So we can record what this program is doing,
我们不知道这是因为这是其他人编写的程序。
which we don't know about because it's a program someone else has written.
我们可以通过查看堆栈跟踪来报告它正在执行的操作，然后说，
And we can report what it was doing by looking at the stack trace and we can say oh,
哦，它花费了大量时间在这个__random_r标准库函数上。
It's spending a bunch of time in this __random_r standard library function.
这主要是因为独占CPU的方法是通过
And it's mainly because the way of hogging a CPU is by
创建越来越多的伪随机数。
just creating more and more pseudo-random numbers.
还有一些未映射的其他函数，
There are some other functions that have not been mapped,
因为它们属于程序，
because they belong to the program,
但如果你知道你的程序，
but if you know about your program
你可以使用更多的标志显示有关perf的信息。
you can display this information using more flags, about perf.
有关如何使用这个工具的非常好的在线教程。
There are really good tutorials online about how to use this tool.
还有一个关于分析器的问题，到目前为止，
Oh One one more thing regarding profilers is, so far,
我们已经看到这些分析器在聚合所有这些信息
we have seen that these profilers are really good at aggregating all this information
并为你提供大量这些数字方面非常出色，
and giving you a lot of these numbers
这样你就可以优化你的代码或者你可以理解正在发生的事情，
so you can optimize your code or you can reason about what is happening,
人类不擅长处理大量数字，
but the thing is humans are not really good at making sense of lots of numbers
而且由于人类更善于视觉处理，
and since humans are more visual creatures,
因此使用可视化工具更容易理解。
it's much easier to kind of have some sort of visualization.
程序员已经想到了解决方法。
Again, programmers have already thought about this and have come up with solutions.
一些流行的可视化工具包括 FlameGraph。
A couple of popular ones, is a FlameGraph.
FlameGraph 是一种采样分析器，
A FlameGraph is a sampling profiler.
通过运行代码并采样来收集数据。
So this is just running your code and taking samples
在 y 轴上，
And then on the y-axis here
我们有堆栈的深度，因此我们知道 bash 函数调用了另一个函数，
we have the depth of the stack so we know that the bash function called this other function,
然后调用了另一个函数，
and this called this other function,
以此类推。
so on, so forth.
在 x 轴上，它不是时间戳，
And on the x-axis it's not time, it's not the timestamps.
而是执行时间。
Like it's not this function run before, but it's just time taken.
因为这是采样分析器：
Because, again, this is a sampling profiler:
我们只能得到程序运行的一些瞬间的样本。
we're just getting small glimpses of what was it going on in the program.
但我们知道
But we know that, for example,
例如这个主程序需要最长的时间，因为 x 轴与此成比例。
this main program took the most time because the x-axis is proportional to that.
它们是交互式的，并且对于确定程序中的热点非常有用。
They are interactive and they can be really useful to identify the hot spots in your program.
另一种显示信息的方法是
Another way of displaying information,
使用调用图，也有关于如何使用这种工具的练习。
and there is also an exercise on how to do this, is using a call graph.
调用图将显示信息，
So a call graph is going to be displaying information,
并创建一个函数调用了哪个其他函数的图。
and it's gonna create a graph of which function called which other function.
然后，您可以获得有关信息，
And then you get information about, like,
例如我们知道 "main" 调用了这个 "Person" 函数十次并且它花费了这么多时间。
oh, we know that "__main__" called this "Person" function ten times and it took this much time.
随着程序越来越大，
And as you have larger and larger programs,
查看其中一个调用图可以帮助确定
looking at one of these call graphs can be useful to identify
您的代码的哪个部分调用了非常昂贵的 IO 操作。
what piece of your code is calling this really expensive IO operation, for example.
最后，我想说的是
With that I'm gonna cover the last part of the lecture,
有时您甚至可能不知道程序中哪个资源受限。
which is that sometimes, you might not even know what exact resource is constrained in your program.
例如，如何知道我的程序使用了多少 CPU，
Like how do I know how much CPU my program is using,
(我可以马上在这里看到)，或者多少内存
(and I can quickly look in there), or how much memory.
因此，有许多非常聪明的工具可以做到这一点，其中之一是 HTOP。
So there are a bunch of really nifty tools for doing that one of them is HTOP.
HTOP 是一个交互式的命令行工具，
so HTOP is an interactive command-line tool
它显示此机器具有的所有 CPU，即 12 个。
and here it's displaying all the CPUs this machine has,which is 12.
它显示内存量，
It's displaying the amount of memory,
并显示我使用了接近 32GB 机器内存中的 1GB。
it says I'm consuming almost a gigabyte of the 32 gigabytes my machine has.
然后我得到了所有不同的进程。
And then I'm getting all the different processes.
例如我们有zsh、mysql和其他在这台机器上运行的进程，
So for example we have zsh, mysql and other processes that are running in this machine,
我可以通过它们消耗的CPU数量
and I can sort through the amount of CPU
或它们运行的优先级进行排序。
they're consuming or through the priority they're running at.
我们可以通过运行stress命令来检查。
We can check this, for example.
在这里，我们再次运行stress命令以占用四个CPU，
Here we have the stress command again and we're going to
并检查我们是否可以在HTOP中看到它们。
run it to take over four CPUs and check that we can see that in HTOP.
我们确实发现了这四个CPU任务，
So we did spot those four CPU jobs, and now I have seen that
现在我发现除了之前我们看到的，现在...
besides the ones we had before, now I have this...
我还有这个“stress -c”命令在运行并占用了我们大量的CPU。
Like this "stress -c" command running and taking a bunch of our CPU.
尽管您可以使用分析器来获取类似于此的信息，
Even though you could use a profiler to get similar information to this,
但是HTOP以实时交互的方式显示此类信息
the way HTOP displays this kind of in a live interactive fashion
可能更快速和更易于解析。
can be much quicker  and much easier to parse.
在笔记中，有一个非常长的列表，列出了用于评估系统不同部分的各种工具。
In the notes, there's a really long list of different tools for evaluating different parts of your system.
那可能是用于分析网络性能的工具，
So that might be tools for analyzing the network performance,
或者查看IO操作的数量，
about looking the number of IO operations,
以便您知道是否饱和了从磁盘读取，
so you know whether you're saturating the reads from your disks,
您还可以查看空间使用情况。
you can also look at what is the space usage.
我想在这里...
Which, I think, here...
NCDU…有一个名为“du”的工具，它代表“磁盘使用”，
So NCDU... There's a tool called "du" which stands for "disk usage" and
我们有“-h”标志用于“人类可读的输出”。
we have the "-h" flag for "human readable output".
我们可以进行视频，然后获得有关此文件夹中所有文件大小的输出。
We can do videos and we can get output about the size of all the files in this folder.
是的，就是这样。
Yeah, there we go.
还有互动版本，例如HTOP是一个互动版本。
There are also interactive versions, like HTOP was an interactive version.
因此，NCDU是一个互动版本，
So NCDU is an interactive version
让我可以浏览文件夹，我可以快速看到哦，
that will let me navigate through the folders and I can see quickly that
emmm...
oh, we have...
这是视频讲座之一的文件夹，
This is one of the folders for the video lectures,
我们可以看到有这四个文件，每个文件大小都接近9 GB，
and we can see there are these four files that have like almost 9 GB each
我可以通过此界面快速删除它们。
and I could quickly delete them through this interface.
另一个很棒的工具是“LSOF”，它代表“打开文件列表”。
Another neat tool is "LSOF" which stands for "LIST OF OPEN FILES".
您可能遇到的另一种模式是，您知道某个进程正在使用文件，
Another pattern that you may encounter is you know some process is using a file,
但您不知道确切是哪个进程在使用该文件。
but you don't know exactly which process is using that file.
或者，类似地，某个进程正在侦听端口，
Or, similarly, some process is listening in a port,
但是，您又如何找出它是哪个进程呢？
but again, how do you find out which one it is?
那么让我们来举个例子。
So to set an example.
我们在444端口上运行一个Python HTTP服务器。
We just run a Python HTTP server on port 444 running there.
也许我们不知道它正在运行，
Maybe we don't know that that's running,
但是我们可以使用……
but then we can
我们可以使用LSOF。
use... we can use LSOF.
是的，我们可以使用LSOF，
Yeah, we can use LSOF,
而LSOF将打印大量信息。
and the thing is LSOF is gonna print a lot of information.
您需要SUDO权限，因为它将要求谁拥有所有这些项。
You need SUDO permissions because this is gonna ask for who has all these items.
由于我们只关心在此444端口上监听的进程，因此我们可以使用grep查询。
Since we only care about the one who is listening in this 444 port we can ask grep for that.
然后我们可以看到，有一个Python进程，具有此标识符，
And we can see, oh, there's like this Python process, with this identifier,
正在使用该端口，然后我们可以将其终止，
that is using the port and then we can kill it,
从而终止该进程。
and that terminates that process.
同样，有许多不同的工具可供使用。
Again, there's a lot of different tools.
甚至有用于进行所谓基准测试的工具。
There's even tools for doing what is called benchmarking.
因此，在Shell工具和脚本讲座中，
So in the shell tools and scripting lecture,
我说过对于某些任务，“fd”比“find”快得多。
I said like for some tasks "fd" is much faster than "find"
但是，如何检查呢？
But like how will you check that?
我可以使用“hyperfine”来测试它，这里有两个命令：
I can test that with "hyperfine" and I have here two commands:
一个使用“fd”仅搜索JPEG文件，另一个使用“find”执行相同的操作。
one with "fd" that is just searching for JPEG files and the same one with "find".
如果我执行它们，它会对这些脚本进行基准测试，
If I execute them, it's gonna benchmark these scripts
并向我提供有关“fd”相对于“find”快多少的一些输出。
and give me some output about how much faster "fd" is compared to "find".
因此，我认为这种总览已经讲完了。
So I think that kind of concludes... yeah, like 23 times for this task.
emmm...
So that kind of concludes the whole overview.
我知道有很多不同的主题
I know that there's like a lot of different topics
和不同的视角来处理这些事情，
and there's like a lot of perspectives on doing these things,
但是我想再次强调的是，
but again I want to reinforce the idea
您不需要成为所有这些主题的专家，
that you don't need to be a master of all these topics but more...
而是要意识到所有这些东西的存在。
To be aware that all these things exist.
因此，如果您遇到这些问题，您不需要重新发明轮子，
So if you run into these issues you don't reinvent the wheel,
而是可以重用其他程序员所做的所有工作。
and you reuse all that other programmers have done.
鉴于此，我很乐意回答与本节或讲座中任何内容有关的问题。
Given that, I'm happy to take any questions related to this last section or anything in the lecture.
有没有什么办法来大概估算程序需要多长时间？
Is there any way to sort of think about how long a program should take?
如果它运行时间较长，
You know, if it's taking a while to run
您是否应该担心？
you know, should you be worried?
或者根据您的进程，
Or depending on your process,
您应该再等十分钟再开始查找为什么它运行时间这么长？
let me wait another ten minutes before I start looking at why it's taking so long.
好的，
Okay, so the...
了解一个程序需要运行多长时间的任务是非常难以确定的，
The task of knowing how long a program should run is pretty infeasible to figure out.
这将取决于程序的类型。
It will depend on the type of program.
这取决于您是在进行HTTP请求还是在读取数据......
It depends on whether you're making HTTP requests or you're reading data...
你可以做的一件事是，
one thing that you can do is if you have for example,
如果你知道你需要从内存或磁盘中读取两个千兆字节的数据，
if you know you have to read two gigabytes from memory, like from disk,
并将其加载到内存中，你可以进行快速的计算。
and load that into memory, you can make back-of-the-envelope calculation.
因为事情是这样安排的，
So like that shouldn't take longer than like X seconds
所以那应该不会超过X秒。
because this is how things are set up.
或者，如果您从网络读取某些文件，
Or if you are reading some files from the network
并且知道网络链接是什么，
and you know kind of what the network link is
并且它们花费的时间比您预期的要长五倍，
and they are taking say five times longer
则可以尝试这样做。
than what you would expect then you could try to do that.
否则，如果您不是很确定。
Otherwise,  if you don't really know.
例如，如果您在代码中尝试进行某些数学操作，
Say you're trying to do some mathematical operation in your code
并且不确定需要多长时间，
and you're not really sure about how long that will take
您可以使用类似于日志记录的方式，
you can use something like logging
并尝试打印中间阶段，
and try to kind of print intermediate stages to get a sense of like,
以了解需要执行多少次操作以及三次迭代花费了十秒钟，
oh I need to do a thousand operations of this and three iterations took ten seconds.
那么在我的情况下，这将需要更长时间才能完成。
Then this is gonna take much longer than I can handle in my case.
所以，我认为有很多方法可以解决这个问题，这又将取决于任务，
So I think there are there are ways, it will again like depend on the task,
但是，鉴于我们看到的所有工具，
but definitely, given all the tools we've seen really,
我们可能有几种很好的方法来开始解决这个问题。
we probably have like a couple of really good ways to start tackling that.
还有其他问题吗？
Any other questions?
您还可以运行HTOP并查看是否有任何正在运行的东西。
You can also do things like run HTOP and see if anything is running.
如果您的CPU使用率为0％，那么可能出了问题。
Like if your CPU is at 0%, something is probably wrong.
好的。今天的课程有很多练习，
Okay. There's a lot of exercises for all the topics that we have covered in today's class,
所以请随意选择您感兴趣的练习。
so feel free to do the ones that are more interesting.
我们今天还将举行办公时间，
We're gonna be holding office hours again today.
只是提醒一下，办公时间。
Just a reminder, office hours.
您可以来问任何关于任何课程的问题。
You can come and ask questions about any lecture.
我们不会期望您在几分钟内完成练习。
Like we're not gonna expect you to kind of do the exercises in a couple of minutes.
他们需要很长时间才能完成，
They take a really long while to get through them,
但是我们将在那里回答关于以前课程的任何问题，
but we're gonna be there to answer any questions from previous classes,
甚至与练习无关的问题。
or even not related to exercises.
例如，如果您想了解
Like if you want to know more about
如何使用TMUX以快速在窗格之间切换，
how you would use TMUX in a way to kind of quickly switch between panes,
以及任何想到的问题。
anything that comes to your mind.